Guide to the Brooklyn Heights Association collection ARC.148
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Heights Association collection
1929-2010
1960s-1970s
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Heights Association
ARC.148
0.75 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and one oversize folder
The Brooklyn Heights Association collection includes newsletters, bulletins, bylaws, annual reports, and correspondence that document the Association's activities. The bulk of the material dates to the 1960s-70s.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This is an artificial composite collection and the exact source and date of acquisition for the collection is unknown. Some of the materials were mailed to the Long Island Historical Society directly.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series 1: Documents and ephemera and Series 2: Publications. Within each series, materials are arranged roughly chronologically.
Historical note
The Brooklyn Heights Association ("BHA") was formed in 1910, and remains the oldest neighborhood association in New York City. Residents and business owners in Brooklyn Heights organized the group to advocate for the improvement and preservation of the neighborhood. The Association formed committees to address issues pertinent to resident and neighborhood concerns, such as civil improvement, police, traffic, parking, trees, and recreation. BHA supported the New York City Landmarks Preservation Law and in 1965, Brooklyn Heights was designated as the first Historic District in New York City. In 2010, BHA celebrated its centennial anniversary and remains an active and influential organization in Brooklyn Heights.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Heights Association Records (BCMS.0035)
Robert Vadheim Brooklyn Heights Association collection (1988.051)
Board of Commissioners for the Improvement of Brooklyn Heights records (1974.161)
Brooklyn Heights Garden Club Collection (BCMS.0082)
Grace Church, Brooklyn Heights collection (ARC.127)
Brooklyn Heights publications in the Local Newspapers on Microfilm collection (BCMS.0028)
Books in the CBH collection:
Brooklyn Heights Association. Enjoying Brooklyn Heights: the Brooklyn Heights Association's self-guided neighborhood walking tour. Brooklyn, NY: Brooklyn Heights Association, [2010]. 974.723 E
Furman, Robert. Brooklyn Heights: the rise, fall and rebirth of America's first suburb. Charleston, SC: The History Press, 2015. 974.723 F
Hanson, Jo Ann. Brooklyn Heights: a case study in historic preservation. 1974. F129.B7 H38p
Krogius, Henrik. The Brooklyn Heights Promenade. Charleston, SC: History Press, [2011]. 974.723 K
Lancaster, Clay. Old Brooklyn Heights: New York's first suburb: including detailed analyses of 619 century-old houses. 1979. 917.4723 L
Langstaff, B. Meredith. Brooklyn Heights: yesterday, today, tomorrow. 1937. F129.B7 L325
Schneider, Martin L. Battling for Brooklyn Heights: the fight for New York's first historic district. Brooklyn, NY: Brooklyn Heights Association, [2010]. 974.723 S
Scope and Contents
Materials in the collection include newsletters, bulletins, bylaws, annual reports, treasurers reports, letters to the general membership, and other correspondence. Newsletters and bulletins constitute a large portion of the collection, detailing the work of the Association and the concerns of members. Topics frequently addressed in newsletters and bulletins include parking, crime, neighborhood appearance, and schools. A significant percentage of the material focuses specifically on the creation of the Brooklyn Heights Historic District in 1965 and historic preservation concerns in the neighborhood in general.
Historic districts |z New York (State) |z New York; Citizens' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic preservation; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Newsletters; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Bulletins; Bylaws (administrative records); Annual reports; Correspondence; Brooklyn Heights Association
- Series 1: Documents and ephemera
  - By-Laws and administrative information, circa 1910-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes 1959 treasurer's report, 1962 list of commercial members, and results from a survey of the membership.
  - Meeting and event programs, 1930s-1940s, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee information and correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, circa 1950s-2010s (Box 1, Folder 4, Box OS-24)
    Includes brochures, mailings, and one oversize meeting poster.
  - Golden Jubilee (50th anniversary), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other organizations, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes Downtown Area Renewal Effort (DARE), Kingsland Preservation Committee, and Committee for Community Building.
  - Letters to members, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Urban Renewal, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes information related to Cobble Hill.
  - 40-44 Remsen Street, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - College Place garages, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - P.S. 8, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cadman Plaza development, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Design Advisory Council, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Historic preservation, 1962-64, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Press releases, 1962, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16, Box OS-24)
  - Annual Report of the President, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Montague Street Committee, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 2: Publications
  - Bulletin, 1929, 1932, 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Newsletters, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - News from BHA, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - BHA Reports, 1978, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter, 1983-1999, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)